Talking about empowerment is odd,
الحديث عن تمكين المرأة أمر غريب،
because when we talk about empowerment,
لأننا عندما نتكلم عنه،
what affects us most are the stories.
فإن أكثر شيء يؤثر بنا هو القصص.
So I want to begin with an everyday story.
لذلك أريد أن أبدأ بقصة من الحياة اليومية.
What is it really like to be a young woman in India?
كيف تكون حقاً حياة امرأة شابة في الهند؟
Now, I've spent the last 27 years of my life
لقد أمضيت آخر 27 عامًا من حياتي
in India, lived in three small towns,
في الهند، عشت في ثلاث بلدات صغيرة
two major cities,
و مدينتين رئيسيتين
and I've had several experiences.
و مررت بالعديد من التجارب.
When I was seven,
عندما كنت في السابعة من عمري
a private tutor who used to come home
كان المدرس الخصوصي الذي يأتي إلي منزلي
to teach me mathematics molested me.
لكي يدرسني الرياضيات، يتحرش بي جنسيًا.
He would put his hand up my skirt.
حيث كان يضع يده أسفل تنورتي.
He put his hand up my skirt and told me
كان يضع يده أسفل تنورتي و يقول لي
he knew how to make me feel good.
أنه يعلم كيف يجعلني أشعر بشعور جيد.
At 17, a boy from my high school
وعندما كنت في 17 من عمري، قام صبي في مدرستي الثانوية
circulated an email
بنشر بريد إلكتروني
detailing all the sexually aggressive things
يحوي تفاصيل كل الأشياء العنيفة جنسيًا
he could do to me
التي يستطيع أن يفعلها بي
because I didn't pay attention to him.
لأنني لم أعره أي اهتمام.
At 19, I helped a friend
و عندما كنت في 19 من عمري، ساعدت صديقتي
whose parents had forcefully married her to an older man
التي أجبرها والداها أن تتزوج من رجل يكبرها في العمر
escape an abusive marriage.
بالهروب من هذا الزواج التعسفي.
At 21, when my friend and I were walking
وعندما كان عمري 21، بينما كنت أتمشى مع صديقتي
down the road one afternoon,
على الطريق عند الظهيرة
a man pulled down his pants
قام رجل بإنزال بنطاله
and masturbated in front of us.
و الاستنماء أمامنا.
We called people for help, and nobody came.
استنجدنا بالناس، لكن لم يأتِ أحد.
At 25, when I was walking home one evening,
و عندما كان عمري 25، و انا عائدة إلى منزلي ذات مساء
two men on a motorcycle attacked me.
قام رجلان على دراجة نارية بمهاجمتي.
I spent two nights in the hospital
عندها أمضيت ليلتين في المستشفى
recovering from trauma and injuries.
لأتعافى من الصدمة و الإصابات.
So throughout my life, I've seen women —
لذلك خلال حياتي، رأيت نساء
family, friends, colleagues —
أُسر و أصدقاء و زملاء
live through these experiences,
يعيشون مثل هذه التجارب
and they seldom talk about it.
و نادرًا ما يتكلمون عنها.
So in simple words, life in India is not easy.
لذلك وبكلمات بسيطة، فإن الحياة في الهند ليست سهلة.
But today I'm not going to talk to you about this fear.
لكنني اليوم لن أتحدث لكم عن هذا الخوف.
I'm going to talk to you about an interesting path
اليوم سأتحدث عن طريق مثير للاهتمام
of learning that this fear took me on.
من التعلم الذي جرني إليه ذلك الخوف.
So, what happened one night in December 2012
إن ما حدث في إحدى ليالي ديسمبر عام 2012
changed my life.
غيّر حياتي .
So a young girl, a 23-year-old student,
طالبة شابة في الثالثة والعشرين من عمرها
boarded a bus in Delhi with her male friend.
استقلت حافلة في دلهي مع صديقها.
There were six men on the bus, young men
كان في الحافلة ستة رجال ، شباب
who you might encounter every day in India,
من الذين يمكن مصادفتهم كل يوم في الهند،
and the chilling account of what followed
و الصدمة سببها ما حدث بعد ذلك
was played over and over again
و الذي حدث مرارًا و تكرارًا
in the Indian and international media.
في الإعلام الهندي و العالمي.
This girl was raped repeatedly,
تم اغتصاب هذه الفتاة بشكل متكرر،
forcefully penetrated with a blunt rod,
كما تم إدخال عصًا حادة لداخلها عنوةً
beaten, bitten, and left to die.
و تم ضربها و عضها و تركت لكي تموت.
Her friend was gagged, attacked,
و صديقها قد سُد فمه وهُوجم
and knocked unconscious.
و ضُرب حتى فقد وعيه.
She died on the 29th of December.
توفيت الفتاة في 29 من ديسمبر.
And at a time when most of us here
و في الوقت الذي كان معظمنا هنا
were preparing to welcome the new year,
يستعدون لاستقبال العام الجديد،
India plunged into darkness.
كانت الهند تنغمس في الظلام.
For the first time in our history,
و لأول مرة في تاريخنا
men and women in Indian cities
استفاق الرجال والنساء
woke up to the horrific truth
على الحقيقة المرعبة
about the true state of women in the country.
لحالة النساء الحقيقة في هذا البلد.
Now, like many other young women,
و مثل الكثير من الشابات الأخريات
I was absolutely terrified.
كنت مذعورة تمامًا.
I couldn't believe that something like this
عجزت عن تصديق أن شيئًا كهذا
could happen in a national capital.
يمكن أن يحدث في عاصمة البلاد.
I was angry and I was frustrated,
كنت غاضبة و محبطة
but most of all, I felt utterly, completely helpless.
و الأهم من ذلك كله شعوري بالعجز المطلق.
But really, what do you do, right?
و لكن ما الذي يمكنك فعله حقًا ؟
Some write blogs, some ignore it,
البعض كتب مدونات و البعض تجاهل القصة
some join protests.
و البعض انضم لاحتجاجات.
I did all of it. In fact, that was what everyone was doing
و قد قمت بكل ذلك، في الواقع .. كان الجميع يفعل ذلك
two years ago.
منذ عامين.
So the media was filled with stories about
لذلك امتلأ الإعلام بقصص
all the horrific deeds
عن كل هذه الأفعال المرعبة
that Indian men are capable of.
التي يستطيع الرجال الهنود القيام بها.
They were compared to animals,
لقد قورنوا بالحيوانات
sexually repressed beasts.
و بالوحوش المكبوتة جنسيًا.
In fact, so alien and unthinkable was this event
في الواقع كان من الغريب وغير الوارد أن يكون هذا الحدث
in an Indian mind
في العقل الهندي
that the response from the Indian media,
لدرجة أن استجابة الإعلام الهندي
public and politicians proved one point:
و رأي العامة و السياسيين أثبت نقطة واحدة :
No one knew what to do.
لا أحد علم الذي يجب فعله.
And no one wanted to be responsible for it.
و لا أحد يريد أن يكون مسؤولاً عن ذلك.
In fact, these were a few insensitive comments
هذه بعض التعليقات الغير حساسة
which were made in the media
ظهرت في الإعلام
by prominent people
بواسطة شخصيات هامة
in response to sexual violence against women in general.
استجابة للعنف الجنسي ضد المرأة. 1(يمكن فهم
So the first one is made by a member of parliament,
اغتصابهن ولا يمكن تخيله مع الأطفال)برلماني
the second one is made by a spiritual leader,
2 (يجب عليهن مناداتهم بالإخوة)زعيم روحي
and the third one was actually the defendants' lawyer
3 (يقع اللوم على الفتيات) محامي دفاع
when the girl was fighting for her life
في حين أن الفتاة كانت تحتضر
and she passed away.
ثم ماتت.
Now, as a woman watching this day after day,
وكامرأة تشاهد هذا يومًا بعد يوم،
I was tired.
كنت أشعر بالتعب.
So as a writer and gender activist,
وبصفتي كاتبة وناشطة جنسانية
I have written extensively on women,
كتبت بشكل مكثف عن المرأة
but this time, I realized it was different,
وأدركت الآن أن ذلك كان مختلفًا
because a part of me realized
لأن جزءًا مني كذلك أدرك
I was a part of that young woman too,
أنه جزء من تلك المرأة الشابة.
and I decided I wanted to change this.
لذا قررت أني أريد لهذا أن يتغير.
So I did something spontaneous, hasty.
فقمت بشيء ما عفوي ومستعجل.
I logged on to a citizen journalism platform
سجلت في صحيفة تعنى بالمواطن
called iReport,
تسمى آي ريبورت،
and I recorded a video talking about
وقمت بتصوير مقطع فيديو عن
what the scene was like in Bangalore.
كيف بدا ذلك المشهد في بانغالور.
I talked about how I felt,
و عن كيف كان شعوري
I talked about the ground realities,
وعن حقائق على الأرض،
and I talked about the frustrations of living in India.
وعن إحباطات العيش في الهند.
In a few hours, the blog was shared widely,
وخلال ساعات انتشرت المدونة بشكل واسع،
and comments and thoughts poured in
وتلقيت سيلًا من الأفكار والتعليقات.
from across the world.
من سائر أرجاء العالم.
In that moment, a few things occurred to me.
وفي تلك اللحظة خطرت ببالي بعض الأمور.
One, technology was always at hand
أولًا أن التقنية في متناول اليد
for many young women like me.
بالنسبة لشابات كثر مثلي.
Two, like me, most young women
وثانيًا أن أكثر الشابات مثلي
hardly use it to express their views.
بالكاد يستعملنها للتعبير عن آرائهن.
Three, I realized for the first time
وثالثًا أني أدركت للمرة الأولى
that my voice mattered.
أن صوتي ذو أهمية.
So in the months that followed,
وفي الأشهر اللاحقة،
I covered a trail of events in Bangalore
قمت بتغطية وتعقب عدة أحداث في بانغالور
which had no space in the mainstream news.
لم يكن لها موقع في الأخبار السائدة.
In Cubbon Park, which is a big park in Bangalore,
وفي منتزه كوبون الكبير ببانغالور
I gathered with over 100 others
اجتمعت ب100 أخريات
when groups of young men came forward
فأقبل علينا جمع من الشباب
to wear skirts to prove that clothing
لارتداء تنورات كي يثبتوا أن اللباس
does not invite rape.
لا يدعو للاغتصاب.
When I reported about these events,
وحين رويت هذه الأحداث،
I felt I had charge, I felt like I had a channel
شعرت بالمسؤولية وأن لدي منفذًا
to release all the emotions I had inside me.
أطلق من خلاله الأحاسيس التي بداخلي.
I attended the town hall march
شاركت بمسيرة إلى البلدية
when students held up signs saying
رفع فيها الطلاب لافتات تقول
"Kill them, hang them."
”اقتلوهم، اشنقوهم“ و ”لن تفعلوا هذا
"You wouldn't do this to your mothers or sisters."
بأمهاتكم أو أخواتكم“
I went to a candlelight vigil
وذهبت ذات عشية في مسيرة بالشموع
where citizens gathered together
حيث اجتمع مواطنون
to talk about the issue of sexual violence openly,
للتحدث حول قضية العنف الجنسي علانية،
and I recorded a lot of blogs
وسجلت عدة تدوينات
in response to how worrying the situation was
استجابة لذلك الوضع المخيف
in India at that point.
في الهند حول تلك القضية.
["I am born with sisters and cousin who now live in cities and abroad but they never talk to me or complain about their daily difficulties like you say"]
"وُلدت مع اخوات وبنات عم يعيشون الآن في المدن وفي الخارج لكنهن لم يتحدثن أو يشكين لي".
Now, the reactions confused me.
أربكتني ردود الفعل.
While supportive comments poured in from across the world,
وبينما انهالت عليّ التعليقات الداعمة
as did vicious ones.
وصلت أيضًا تعليقات خبيثة.
So some called me a hypocrite.
نعتني البعض بالمنافقة.
Some called me a victim, a rape apologist.
وآخرون بالمعتذرة للضحية.
Some even said I had a political motive.
فيما قال البعض أن لدي دافع سياسي.
But this one comment kind of describes
لكن هذا التعليق يصف نوعًا ما
what we are discussing here today.
ما نناقشه الآن.
But I was soon to learn that this was not all.
ثم كنت لأتعلم مبكرًا أن هذا لم يكن كل شيء.
As empowered as I felt
و كمُفوضة كما شعرت
with the new liberty that this
مع الحرية الجديدة التي وهبني
citizen journalism channel gave me,
منفذ صحافة المواطن،
I found myself in an unfamiliar situation.
وجدت نفسي في موقف عجيب.
So sometime last August, I logged onto Facebook
في أغسطس الماضي دخلت فيسبوك
and I was looking through my news feed,
كنت أطالع المستجدات،
and I noticed there was a link
لفت نظري رابط
that was being shared by my friends.
تشاركه أصدقائي
I clicked on the link; it led me back
ضغطت عليه؛ لقد أعادني للوراء
to a report uploaded by an American girl
لتقرير رفعته فتاة أمريكية
called Michaela Cross.
تدعى ميكيلا كروس.
The report was titled,
كان عنوانه:
"India: The story you never wanted to hear."
”الهند: القصة التي لم ترد أبدًا سماعها“
And in this report, she recounted her firsthand
وفي تقريرها، قصت باكورة حديثها
account of facing sexual harassment in India.
عن مواجهتها للتحرش الجنسي في الهند.
She wrote, "There is no way to prepare for the eyes,
كتبت ”لم يكن من طريقة لتحاشي نظر العيون
the eyes that every day stared
تلك التي كانت تحدق في جسدي
with such entitlement at my body,
كل يوم وباستحقاق مزعوم،
with no change of expression
ودون تغير في التعبير
whether I met their gaze or not.
واجهت التحديق أم لم أفعل.
Walking to the fruit seller's or the tailor's,
سواء مشيت لبائع فاكهة أو خياط،
I got stares so sharp
تلقيت نظرات حادة
that they sliced away bits of me piece by piece."
قطعتني إربًا إربًا.“
She called India a traveler's heaven and a woman's hell.
لقد سمت الهند جنة المسافر وجحيم المرأة.
She said she was stalked, groped,
قالت أنه تم التحرش بها،
and masturbated at.
والاستمناء عليها.
Now, late that evening, the report went viral.
انتشر التقرير كالنار في الهشيم.
It was on news channels across the world.
أصبح في الأخبار في أرجاء العالم.
Everyone was discussing it.
كان الكل يناقشه. وقد حصل على
It had over a million views,
أكثر من مليون مشاهدة،
and I found myself witnessing
ووجدت نفسي شاهدة
a very similar thing.
على شيء مشابه جدًا.
The media was caught in this vicious cycle
ضُبط الإعلام في هذه الدائرة المفرغة
of opinion and outburst
بالآراء والهيجان
and no outcome whatsoever.
ودون نتيجة تذكر.
So that night, as I sat wondering
جلست تلك الليلة أتساءل
how I should respond,
كيف يجب أن أرد،
I found myself filled with doubt.
فوجدت نفسي ملأى بالشكوك.
You see, as a writer, I approached this issue
تعلمون أني ككاتبة درست القضية،
as an observer,
و كراصدة وهندية،
as an Indian, I felt embarrassment and disbelief,
شعرت بالعار وعدم تصديق ذلك،
and as an activist, I looked at it as a defender of rights,
وكناشطة نظرت لها بصفتي محامية عن الحقوق
but as a citizen journalist,
ولكني شعرت فجأة أني ضعيفة،
I suddenly felt very vulnerable.
بصفتي صحفية مدنية.
I mean, here she was, a young woman
أعني أنه كان هنا شابة
who was using a channel to talk about
وظفت قناتها للتحدث عن تجربتها
her experience just as I was,
كما فعلت بالضبط،
and yet I felt unsettled.
ورغم هذا شعرت بالقلق.
You see, no one ever tells you
كما ترون لم يخبركم أحد أبدًا
that true empowerment comes from giving yourself
أن التمكين الحق يحدث حين تسمح لنفسك
the permission to think and act.
أن تفكر وتعمل.
Empowerment is often made to sound as if
إن التمكين يحدث عادة ليبدو كصفقة
it's an ideal, it's a wonderful outcome.
إنه نتيجة مذهلة.
When we talk about empowerment, we often
حين نتحدث عن التمكين فنحن عادة
talk about giving people access to materials,
نتحدث عن السماح بالوصول المواد
giving them access to tools.
و تسهيل الوصول للأدوات.
But the thing is, empowerment is an emotion.
إن الأهم في التمكين هو الشعور.
It's a feeling.
إنه الإحساس.
The first step to empowerment
الخطوة الأولى نحو التمكين
is to give yourself the authority,
أن تمنح نفسك السلطة،
the key to independent will,
والمفتاح للإرادة المستقلة،
and for women everywhere,
و لنا نحن النساء في كل مكان،
no matter who we are or where we come from,
بصرف النظر عمن نكون أو من أتينا،
that is the most difficult step.
وتلك هي الخطوة الأصعب.
We fear the sound of our own voice,
إننا نخشى أصواتنا،
for it means admission, but it is this that gives us
لأنها تعني التسليم، لكنه ذلك الذي يمنحنا
the power to change our environment.
القوة كي نغير محيطنا.
Now in this situation where I was faced
وفي هذا الموقف الذي واجهت فيه الكثير
with so many different kinds of realities,
من مختلف الحقائق
I was unsure how to judge,
كنت غير واثقة كيف سأحكم
because I didn't know what it would mean for me.
إذ أنني لم أعلم ما الذي سيعني ذلك لي.
I feared to judge because I didn't know what it would be
خشيت أن أحكم فأنا لم أعرف كيف سيبدو الأمر
if I didn't support the same view as this girl.
إن لم أدعم رأي هذه الفتاة.
I didn't know what it would mean for me
لم أعرف كيف سيبدو الأمر
if I was challenging someone else's truth.
إن تحديت حقيقة شخص آخر.
But yet, it was simple.
وبرغم ذلك لقد كان الأمر بسيطًا.
I had to make a decision:
وجب علي اتخاذ قرار:
Should I speak up or should I stay quiet?
هل علي أن أجهر بحديثي أم ألتزم الصمت؟
So after a lot of thought,
وبعد تفكير عميق،
I recorded a video blog in response,
قمت بتسجيل مرئي لجوابي،
and I told Michaela, well,
وأخبرت ميكيلا أن هناك الكثير
there are different sides to India,
من الجوانب المختلفة في الهند،
and I also tried to explain
وحاولت كذلك أن أوضح
that things would be okay
أن الأمور ستسير على ما يرام بعد أيام،
and I expressed my regret for what she had faced.
كما عبرت عن أسفي لما تعرضت له.
And a few days later, I was invited to talk
وبعد أيام قلائل دُعيتُ
on air with her,
لمحادثة مباشرة معها،
and for the first time, I reached out to this girl
وللمرة الأولى وصلت لهذه الفتاة
who I had never met, who was so far away,
التي لم أقابلها، والتي كانت بعيدة جدًا،
but yet I felt so close to.
ومع كل ذلك فقد شعرت بالقرب منها.
Since this report came to light,
منذ ظهر هذا التقرير للنور
more young people than ever
والكثير من الشباب يناقشون التحرش الجنسي
were discussing sexual harassment on the campus,
في الحرم الجامعي كما لم يفعلوا من قبل
and the university that Michaela belonged to
بل وقامت الجامعة التي تنتمي لها ميكيلا
gave her the assistance she needed.
بتقديم العون لها.
The university even took measures
كما اتخذت الجامعة إجراءات
to train its students to equip them
لتدريب طالباتها وتزويدهن
with the skills that they need
بالمهارات المطلوبة
to confront challenges such as harassment,
لمواجهة التحديات كالتحرش مثلًا،
and for the first the time, I felt I wasn't alone.
وللمرة الأولى غمرني شعور أني لست وحيدة.
You see, if there's anything that I've learned
و إن كان من شيء تعلمته في السنوات السابقة
as an active citizen journalist
كصحفية مدنية وناشطة
over the past few years,
طوال هذه السنين،
it is our dire lack as a society to actively find
فهو غلطنا الفادح كمجتمع في أن نبحث
avenues where our voices can be heard.
بنشاط عن سبل كي تسمع أصواتنا.
We don't realize that when we are standing up,
إننا نجهل أنا حين نناضل
we are not just standing up as individuals,
فلسنا نناضل كأفراد،
we are standing up for our communities,
بل نناضل عن مجتمعاتنا
our friends, our peers.
وأصدقائنا وأقراننا.
Most of us say that women are denied their rights,
ربما يقول أكثرنا أن النساء يُمنعن حقوقهن،
but the truth is, oftentimes,
لكن الحقيقة تقول أنه لطالما
women deny themselves these rights.
حرمت النساء أنفسهن هذه الحقوق.
In a recent survey in India,
وفي دراسة مسحية حديثة في الهند،
aviation, hospitality and call centers,
والملاحة والفندقة ومراكز الاتصال أنهن لم
said they didn't feel safe returning home alone
يشعرن بالأمان حال العودة للمنزل بمفردهن
after work in the late hours or in the evening.
عقب عمل في ساعات متأخرة من الليل.
In Bangalore, where I come from,
وفي بانغالور؛ التي أنتمي لها
this number is 85 percent.
فإن الرقم هو 85%.
In rural areas in India,
وفي المناطق الريفية في الهند،
if anything is to go by the recent
إن كان حكمنا هو على الآونة الأخيرة فإنّ
gang rapes in Badaun and acid attacks in Odisha
حوادث الاغتصاب الجماعي في بادوان وهجمات
and Aligarh are supposed to go by,
الأسيد في أوديشا وأليغرا ستكون مقبولة.
we need to act really soon.
إن علينا التحرك بسرعة.
Don't get me wrong,
لا تسيؤوا فهمي،
the challenges that women will face
فالتحديات التي تواجه النساء،
in telling their stories is real,
في رواية قصصهن حقيقية،
but we need to start pursuing
ولكن علينا محاولة السعي لتحصيل
to participate in our system
للمشاركة في نظامنا اليوم،
and not just pursue the media blindly.
وليس السعي الأعمى خلف وسائل الإعلام.
Today, more women than ever
وفي الوقت الحاضر تناضل النساء
are standing up and questioning
ويستجوبن الحكومة الهندية
the government in India,
كما لم يفعلن من قبل،
and this is a result of that courage.
وهذا نتيجة لتلك الشجاعة.
There is a sixfold increase in women
وهناك زيادة بستة أضعاف في بلاغ
reporting harassment,
النساء عن التحرش الجنسي
and the government passed
كما أقرت الحكومة تعديل
the Criminal Law (Amendment) Act in 2013
لائحة القانون الجنائي سنة 2013
to protect women against sexual assault.
لحماية النساء من الاعتداء الجنسي.
I just want to say
أود القول أني أعلم أنّ الكثير منا
that I know a lot of us in this room have our secrets,
في هذه القاعة يملك أسرارًا
but let us speak up.
ولكن دعونا نجهر بأصواتنا.
Let us fight the shame and talk about it.
ولنتغلب على العار ونكشفها.
It could be a platform, a community,
قد تكون منصة أو مجتمعًا
your loved one, whoever or whatever you choose,
أو حبيبًا ذاك الذي نختاره،
but let us speak up.
مهما يكن، لنتكلم بصوت عال.
The truth is, the end to this problem
إن الحقيقة تقول أن النهاية لهذه المشكلة
begins with us.
تبدأ من خلالنا نحن .
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم